<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 93 $ on 26.02.2011 07:39:58[cl1n033] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Pasta</title>
<id>23871</id>
<revision>
<id>374964513</id>
<timestamp>2010-07-23T02:42:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>L Kensington</username>
<id>12666844</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Greek loanwords</category>
<category>:Mediterranean cuisine</category>
<category>:Noodles</category>
<category>:Pasta</category>
<category>:Staple foods</category>
<category>:Italian loanwords</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>


<image width="239px" src="Pasta_Venice.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Different types of pasta on display in a shop window.
</caption>
</image>

<p>

<b>Pasta</b> is a generic term for foods made from an unleavened dough of wheat or buckwheat, flour and water, sometimes with other ingredients such as eggs and vegetable extracts. Pastas include noodles in various lengths, widths and shapes, and varieties that are filled with other ingredients like ravioli and tortellini. The word pasta is also used to refer to dishes in which pasta products are a primary ingredient. It is usually served with sauce.</p>
<p>

There are hundreds of different shapes of pasta with at least locally recognized names.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Examples include spaghetti (thin rods), macaroni (tubes or cylinders), <it>fusilli</it> (swirls), and <it>lasagne</it> (sheets). Two other noodles, <it>gnocchi</it> and <it>spätzle</it>, are sometimes considered pasta. They are both traditional in parts of Italy. </p>
<p>

Pasta is categorized in two basic styles: <it>dried</it> and <it>fresh</it>. Dried pasta made without eggs can be stored for up to two years under ideal conditions, while fresh pasta will keep for a few days in the fridge.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Pasta is generally cooked by boiling.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Etymology</st>
<p>

First attested in English 1874, the word <it>pasta</it> comes from Italian <it>pasta</it>, it turn from Latin <it>pasta</it> "dough, pastry cake", itself the romanization of the Greek παστά (<it>pasta</it>) "barley porridge", in turn from "παστός" (<it>pastos</it>), " sprinkled with salt, salted".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ingredients</st>
<p>

Image:Pasta Machine.jpg|left|thumb|200px|A small pasta machine designed to mangle lasagne and cut tagliatelle.]] </p>
<p>

Under Italian law, dry pasta (<it>pasta secca</it>) can only be made from durum sticks wheat flour or durum wheat semolina.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Durum flour and durum semolina have a yellow tinge in color. Italian pasta is traditionally cooked <it>al dente</it> (Italian: "firm to the bite", meaning not too soft). Outside Italy, dry pasta is frequently made from other types of flour (such as wheat flour), but this yields a softer product that cannot be cooked <it>al dente</it> the same way. There are many types of wheat flour with varying gluten and protein depending on variety of grain used.</p>
<p>

Particular varieties of pasta may also use other grains and milling methods to make the flour, as specified by Italian law.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Some pasta varieties, such as pizzoccheri, are made from buckwheat flour. Fresh pasta may include eggs (<it>pasta all'uovo</it> 'egg pasta'). Whole wheat pasta, which generally contains more fiber and more nutrients than refined pasta, has become increasingly popular.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>  Whole wheat pasta designed to appeal to people familiar with refined grain pastas may have a mixture of whole grain and refined grain ingredients.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="200px" src="Moser_Spaghetti_essender_Junge.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<it>Boy with Spaghetti</it> by Julius Moser, c. 1808.
</caption>
</image>

Image:6-alimenti, pasta,Taccuino Sanitatis, Casanatense 4182..jpg|thumb|Making pasta; illustration from the 15th century edition of <it>Tacuinum Sanitatis</it>, a Latin translation of the Arabic work <it>Taqwīm al-sihha</it> by Ibn Butlan.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>]]</p>
<p>

Pasta's origin continues to evoke speculation. While many different cultures ate some sort of noodle-like food, composed mostly of grain, the key characteristics of pasta are durum wheat semolina, with a high gluten content. Furthermore, it is made with a technique that allows the resultant dough to be highly malleable, thus resulting in the many different shapes (i.e., ziti, spaghetti, ravioli) that characterize "pasta."  In North Africa, a food similar to pasta, known as couscous, has been eaten for centuries.  However, it lacks the distinguishing malleable nature of what is now referred to as pasta, couscous being more akin to droplets of dough.  In China, noodles of millet or rice have been eaten for centuries, but lack the durum wheat semolina paste that denotes pasta.  </p>
<p>

Historians have noted several lexical milestones relevant to pasta, none which change these basic characteristics.  For example, the works of the 2nd century AD Greek physician Galen mention <it>itrion</it>, homogeneous compounds made up of flour and water.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> The Jerusalem Talmud records that <it>itrium</it>, a kind of boiled dough,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> was common in Palestine from the 3rd to 5th centuries AD,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> A dictionary compiled by the 9th century Syrian physician and lexicographer Isho bar Ali<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> defines <it>itriyya</it>,  the Arabic cognate, as string-like shapes made of semolina and dried before cooking.  The geographical text of Muhammad al-Idrisi, compiled for the Norman King of Sicily Roger II in 1154 mentions <it>itriyya</it> manufactured and exported from Norman Sicily:
</p>
<p>

<it>Itriyya</it> gives rise to <it>trie</it> in Italian, signifying long strips such as <it>tagliatelle</it> and <it>trenette</it>. One form of <it>itriyya</it> with a long history is <it>laganum</it> (plural <it>lagana</it>), which in Latin refers to a thin sheet of dough,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> and gives rise to Italian <it>lasagna</it>.</p>
<p>

Image:Lasagna.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Lasagna]]</p>
<p>

The Chinese were eating noodles made of millet as long ago as 2000 BC. This has been suggested by the discovery of a well-preserved bowl of millet noodles over 4000 years old.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> However, durum wheat was not known in China until later times. The familiar legend of Marco Polo importing pasta from China<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> originated with the  <it>Macaroni Journal</it>, published by an association of food industries with the goal of promoting the use of pasta in the United States.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>  Marco Polo describes a food similar to "lagana" in his <it>Travels</it>, but he uses a term with which he was already familiar. Durum wheat, and thus pasta as it is known today, was introduced by Arabs during their conquest of Sicily in the late 7th century, according to the newsletter of the National Macaroni Manufacturers Association,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> thus predating Marco Polo's travels to China by about six centuries.</p>
<p>

In the 1st century BC writings of Horace, <it>lagana</it> were fine sheets of dough which were fried<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> and were an everyday food.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> Writing in the 2nd century Athenaeus of Naucratis provides a recipe for <it>lagana</it> which he attributes to the 1st century Chrysippus of Tyana: sheets of dough made of wheat flour and the juice of crushed lettuce, then flavored with spices and deep-fried in oil.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> An early 5th century cookbook describes a dish called <it>lagana</it> that consisted of layers of dough with meat stuffing, a possible ancestor of modern-day <it>Lasagna</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> But the method of cooking these sheets of dough does not correspond to our modern definition of either a fresh or dry pasta product. The first concrete information concerning pasta products in Italy dates from the thirteenth or fourteenth century.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> The name (λαγάνα, <it>lagána</it>) survives in modern-day Greece to denote an unleavened, flat bread eaten during the Great Lent. The term "lagana" is also used in the Southern region of Calabria, where it indicates a flat noodle.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Varieties</st>
<p>


<image width="150px" src="Pasta_2006_1.jpg">
<caption>

Long Pasta
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Pasta_2006_2.jpg">
<caption>

Short Pasta
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Pasta_2006_3.jpg">
<caption>

Short Pasta
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Pasta_2006_4.jpg">
<caption>

Minute Pasta (<it>Pastina</it>, used for soups)
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Pasta_2006_5.jpg">
<caption>

<it>Pasta all'uovo</it> (egg pasta)
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Pasta_2006_6.jpg">
<caption>

Fresh Pasta
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Pasta_2006_7.jpg">
<caption>

Pasta for <it>Pasta al forno</it> (baked pasta) dishes
</caption>
</image>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Accompaniments </st>
<p>

Image:Pasta with pesto.jpg|right|thumb|250px|<it>Pesto Cavatappi</it>]]</p>
<p>

Pasta is generally served with some type of sauce; the sauce and the type of pasta are usually matched based on consistency, ease of eating, etc. Common pasta sauces in Northern Italy include pesto and ragù alla bolognese, which usually adds meat to the sauce.  In Central Italy, there are simple sauces such as tomato sauce, amatriciana and carbonara.  Southern Italian sauces include spicy tomato, garlic, and olive oil, with the pasta often paired with fresh vegetables or seafood. Varieties include puttanesca, <it>pasta alla norma</it> (tomatoes, eggplant and fresh or baked cheese), <it>pasta con le sarde</it> (fresh sardines, pine nuts, fennel and olive oil), <it>spaghetti aglio, olio e peperoncino</it> (literally with garlic, [olive] oil and hot chili peppers).</p>
<p>

<image location="left" width="210px" src="Tagliolini1.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Fresh pasta
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Fettuccine alfredo with cream and cheese, and spaghetti with tomato sauce (with or without meat) are popular Italian-style dishes in the United States.</p>
<p>

As pasta was introduced elsewhere in the world, it became incorporated into a number of local cuisines, which often have significantly different ways of preparation from those of Italy.  In Hong Kong, the local Chinese have adopted pasta, primarily spaghetti and macaroni, as an ingredient in the Hong Kong-style Western cuisine.  In Cha chaan teng, macaroni is cooked in water and served in broth with ham or frankfurter sausages, peas, black mushrooms, and optionally eggs, reminiscent of noodle soup dishes. This is often a course for breakfast or light lunch fare.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>  This method often involves cooking the pasta well beyond the al dente stage and washing the starches off the pasta after cooking, measures frowned upon in Italy or in Hong Kong's more authentic Italian eateries.</p>
<p>

Two common spaghetti dishes served in Japan are the Bolognese (ミートソース) and the Napolitan (ナポリタン). In India, macaroni has been adopted and cooked in an Indianized way. Boiled macaroni is sautéed along with jeera, turmeric, finely chopped green chillies, onions &amp; cabbage. In Greece hilopittes is considered one of the finest types of dried egg pasta. It is cooked either in tomato sauce or with various kinds of casserole meat. It is usually served with Greek cheese of any type. Pasta is also widespread in Argentina and Brazil, especially in the areas with strong Italian roots, like Buenos Aires and São Paulo. The local names for the pasta are varieties of the Italian names, such as ñoquis/nhoque for gnocchi, ravioles/ravióli for ravioli, or tallarines/talharim for tagliatelle. In Sweden, spaghetti is traditionally served with köttfärssås, which is minced meat in a thick tomato soup. In the Philippines, spaghetti is often served with a distinct, slightly sweet yet flavorful meat sauce, frequently containing diced hot dogs.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cooking</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Italian cuisine</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

National Pasta Association</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>



<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.archimedes-lab.org/pastashape.html">
Pasta shapes</weblink> – History and an abridged list of pasta shapes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pastacanada.com/english/pastafacts/pastafacts.html">
Pasta Facts</weblink> – Facts about pasta</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scientificpsychic.com/alpha/food/ravioli-dumplings-pierogi.html">
Making Dumplings</weblink> – How to make ravioli, dumplings, and pierogi, including striped and colored pasta.</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
