<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] with modifications for the NTCIR Crosslink project on 21.03.2012 13:18:38[centos6] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Tom yum</title>
<id>1261868</id>
<revision>
<id>468613383</id>
<timestamp>2011-12-30T15:51:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Vagobot</username>
<id>14632721</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Lao soups</category>
<category>:Soups</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>


<image width="150px" src="Tom_yum.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<it>Tom yum goong</it> in Japan
</caption>
</image>

File:Tomyumsoup.png|thumb|<it>Tom yum goong</it> as served in Bangkok, Thailand.]]
File:Tom yam kung maphrao on nam khon.jpg|thumb|<it>Tom yum goong maphrao on nam khon</it>, as served in Uttaradit, Thailand]]
<b>Tom yum</b> or <b>tom yam</b> (Lao: ຕົ້ມຍຳ ; , ) is the name for a spicy clear soup typical in Laos and Thailand. Tom yum is widely served in neighboring countries such as Malaysia, Singapore, and Indonesia, and has been popularized around the world.  It is listed at number 8 on <it>World's 50 Most Delicious Foods</it> complied by <it>CNN Go</it> in 2011.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

Literally, the words "tom yum" are derived from two Lao-Thai words: "tom" and "yum". "Tom" refers to boiling process (soup, in this case). "Yum" refers to a kind of Lao-Thai spicy and sour salad. Thus, "tom-yum" is a Lao-Thai hot and sour soup. Indeed, tom yum is characterized by its distinct hot and sour flavors, with fragrant herbs generously used in the broth. The basic broth is made of stock and fresh ingredients such as lemon grass, kaffir lime leaves, galangal, lime juice, fish sauce and crushed chili peppers.</p>
<p>

In neighbouring countries like Singapore, Malaysia and Indonesia, the name <it>tom yum</it> is used widely for various spicy soups which can differ greatly from true Lao-Thai tom yum soup. As a result, people are often confused by the disparities. </p>
<p>

Commercial tom yum paste is made by crushing all the herb ingredients and stir frying in oil. Seasoning and other preservative ingredients are then added. The paste is bottled or packaged, and sold around the world. Tom yum flavored with the paste may have different characteristics from that made with fresh herb ingredients.</p>
<p>

The 1997 Financial Crisis in Asia, which started in Thailand, is sometimes referred to as the "Tom Yam Kung Crisis".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Selected types</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tom yum goong</it> or <it>tom yam kung</it>, the version of the dish most popular among tourists is made with prawns as main ingredient.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tom yum goong maphrao on nam khon</it>, a version of prawn tom yum with the meat of a young coconut and a dash of coconut milk.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tom yum paa</it> (Lao) or <it>Tom yum pla</it> (Thai) is a clear fish soup that was traditionally eaten with rice. It used to be the most widespread form of <it>tom yam</it> before mass-tourism came to Thailand, for fresh fish is readily available almost everywhere in the region's rivers, canals and lakes as well as in the sea. Usually fish with firm flesh that doesn't crumble after boiling is preferred for this type of soup.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tom yum gai</it> or <it>tom yam kai</it> is the chicken version of the soup.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tom yum po taek</it> (Lao) or <it>Tom yum thale</it> (Thai) is a variant of the soup with mixed seafood, like prawns, squid, clams and pieces of fish. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tom yum nam khon</it> () is a more recent variation. Almost always made with prawns as a main ingredient, a little coconut milk is added to the broth as a finishing touch, and then balanced with some toasted dried chillies. This adaptation is not to be confused with <it>tom kha gai</it> ("chicken galanga soup"), where galanga is the dominant flavour of the coconut milk-based soup.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tom yam kha mu</it> (), made with pork knuckles. These require a long cooking time under low fire.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In the modern popularized versions the soup contains also mushrooms - usually straw mushrooms or oyster mushrooms. The soup is often topped with generous sprinkling of fresh chopped cilantro (coriander leaves). Sometimes Thai chili jam (<it>nam phrik phao</it>, ) is added: this gives the soup a bright orange color and makes the chili flavor more pronounced.
The Royal Lao version of tom yam includes a pinch of rice in the soup.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Tom khlong</st>
<p>

Less well-known outside Thailand is <it>tom khlong</it> (ต้มโคล้ง), a similar spicy sour soup where the sourness, however, does not derive from lime juice but through the use of tamarind.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>


<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lao cuisine</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Thai cuisine</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

List of Thai ingredients</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
CNN Go <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnngo.com/explorations/eat/worlds-50-most-delicious-foods-067535">
World's 50 most delicious foods</weblink> 21 July 2011. Retrieved 2011-10-11</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hu.ac.th/academic/article/Mk/Hamburger%20Crisis.htm">
From Tom-yam-kung To Hamburger Crisis</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thaiwaysmagazine.com/thai_article/2008_tom_yam_kung/tom_yam_kung.html">
Thaiways - Tom yam kung</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spicecuisine.com/tom_yam_pla.php">
Clear Fish Soup, a Thai food recipe from Thailand</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.melroseflowers.com/mkic/intl_cuisine/thai/sour_and_spicy_chicken_soup.html">
Sour and Spicy Chicken Soup (Tom Yam Kai)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spicecuisine.com/tom_yam_talay.php">
<it>Tom yam talay - Clear and spicy seafood soup</it></weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TBqO5s0qDVE">
ต้มยำขาหมู</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.allthaifood.com/recipes/3-302-1/tom-klong-pla-krob-(%E0%B8%95%E0%B9%89%E0%B8%A1%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%A5%E0%B9%89%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%9B%E0%B8%A5%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%9A).html">
Tom klong pla krob (ต้มโคล้งปลากรอบ)</weblink></entry>
</reflist>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>


<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.khiewchanta.com/archives/soups/curry-soups/tom-yam-fish-eggs-tom-yam-kai.html">
Tom Yam Fish Eggs ( Tom Yam Kai Pla ) - Appon's Thai Food Recipes</weblink></entry>
</list>


</p>

<p>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
