<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] with modifications for the NTCIR Crosslink project on 21.03.2012 13:18:37[centos6] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Tieguanyin</title>
<id>961283</id>
<revision>
<id>468237481</id>
<timestamp>2011-12-29T09:12:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Qeny</username>
<id>4314838</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Oolong tea</category>
<category>:Chiuchow cuisine</category>
<category>:China famous tea</category>
<category>:Chinese tea grown in Fujian</category>
<category>:Chinese tea grown in Taiwan</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>



File:20090606 Putuoshan 8786.jpg|thumb|right|Statue of Guanyin at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/709/438709.xml">
Mount Putuo</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/602/96602.xml">
Zhejiang</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/405/5405.xml">
China</link>]]
<b><it>Tieguanyin</it></b> ( or 'Tikuanyin' / 'Tit Koon Yum') is a premium variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/405/5405.xml">
Chinese</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/707/22707.xml">
oolong tea</link> originated in the 19th century in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/520/3236520.xml">
Anxi</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/585/88585.xml">
Fujian province</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Tieguanyin produced in different areas of Anxi have different gastronomic characteristics.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  Production has since extended to many regions even outside of China, including Mucha in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/651/303651.xml">
Nantou</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/107/30107.xml">
Taiwan</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>
<sec>
<st>
Etymology</st>
<p>

The tea is named after the Chinese Goddess of Mercy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/063/17063.xml">
Guanyin</link>, who is known in Japan as Kannon and in Korea as Guam-eum. Guanyin is a female embodiment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/425/241425.xml">
Avalokiteśvara</link> Bodhisattva <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

The name of the Chinese tea is translated in English as "Iron Guanyin", and sometimes as "Iron Goddess of Mercy." These two names are accurate.  The deity has long been given a female identity in Chinese folk culture, although the original Chinese name carries no suggestion of the male-or-female-nature.  A more accurate translation of the reference to the deity should be (the One) Observing the Voice of the People.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Other spellings and names include "Ti Kuan Yin," "Tit Kwun Yum," "Ti Kwan Yin," "Iron Buddha," "Iron Goddess Oolong," and "Tea of the Iron Bodhisattva." It is also known in the abbreviated form as "TGY."</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Legends</st>
<p>

There are two legends behind this tea: Wei and Wang.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Wei legend</st>
<p>

Deep in the heart of Fujian's Anxi County, there was a rundown temple which held an iron statue of Guanyin, the Bodhisattva of Compassion. Every day on the walk to his tea fields, a poor farmer named Mr. Wei would pass by and reflect on the temple's worsening condition. “Something has to be done,” thought Mr. Wei. </p>
<p>

Being poor, he did not have the means to repair the temple. Instead, the farmer brought a broom and some incense from his home. He swept the temple clean and lit the incense as an offering to Guanyin. "It's the least I can do," he thought to himself. Twice a month for many months, he repeated the same tasks. </p>
<p>

One night, Guanyin appeared to him in a dream. She told him of a cave behind the temple where treasure awaited. He was to take the treasure and share it with others. In the cave, the farmer found a single tea shoot. He planted it in his field and nurtured it into a large bush, from which the finest tea was produced. He gave cuttings of this rare plant to all his neighbors and began selling the tea under the name Tieguanyin, Iron Bodhisattva of Compassion. </p>
<p>

Over time, Mr. Wei and all his neighbors prospered; the rundown temple of Guanyin was repaired and became a beacon for the region.  Mr. Wei took joy in the daily trip to his tea fields, never failing to stop in appreciation of the beautiful temple.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Wang legend</st>
<p>

Wang was a scholar who accidentally discovered the tea plant beneath the Guanyin rock in Xiping. He brought the plant back home for cultivation. When he visited <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/949/265949.xml">
Emperor Qianlong</link> in the 6th year of his reign, he offered the tea as a gift from his native village. Emperor Qianlong was so impressed that he inquired about its origin. Since the tea was discovered beneath the Guanyin Rock, he decided to call it the Guanyin tea.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Processing of Tieguanyin Tea</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Tie_Guan_Yin_processing_chart.GIF">
<caption>

Processing Chart of Tieguanyin tea.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The processing of Tieguanyin tea (TGY) is complex and requires expertise. Even if the tea leaf is of high raw quality, and is plucked at the ideal time, if it is not processed correctly its true character will not be shown. This is why the method of processing Tieguanyin Tea was kept a secret. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 plucking tea leaves ()</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 sun withering ()</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 cooling ()</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 tossing ()</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 withering, this includes some oxidation. ()</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 fixation ()</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 rolling ()</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 drying ()</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

After drying some teas go through the added processes of roasting and scenting. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Varieties</st>
<p>

By roasting level:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Jade Tieguanyin</it> (lightly baked Tieguanyin) is a newer type of Tieguanyin and has a light green jade color. It produces a very flowery aroma and taste. It is more similar to green tea than Oolong.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Thoroughly Baked Tieguanyin</it> is the original style. It has a more complex taste profile and warm aroma, but the traditional baking technique has not been passed on well so quality ones of this style is less seen in the market than "moderately baked' and "lightly" baked versions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Moderately baked Tieguanyin</it> is a new breed that some argue has a good balance of floral aroma and complex taste, but it stores poorly.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></entry>
</list>

By harvest time:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Spring Tieguanyin</it> is harvested around Li Xia (Start of Summer) and has the best overall quality.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Autumn Tieguanyin</it> is harvested in the autumn and has strong aroma but less complex taste.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Summer Tieguanyin</it> is harvested in summer and is considered lower quality. Summer Tieguanyin can be further divided into two types one harvested in June to July, one harvested in August.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Winter Tieguanyin</it> is harvested in winter. Production of Winter Tieguanyin is very low.</entry>
</list>

Other categories:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Guanyin Wang</it> (Guanyin "King") is the best of Jade Tieguanyin and Autumn Tieguanyin.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Types</st>
<p>

Based on the different roasting methods and locations, the types of Tieguanyin are various.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Chinese Anxi Iron Goddess Tea 安溪鉄観音- This oolong is typically close to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/676/262676.xml">
green tea</link>, with only a little <link>
oxidation</link>. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> With a very flowery and fresh delicate aroma character, the tea liquid is golden yellow. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Taiwan Mucha Iron Goddess Tea 木柵鉄観音- This traditional oolong is roasted and has a stronger taste and with roast nutty character, the tea liquid is reddish-brown.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/245/31075245.xml">
Taiwan teas</link></entry>
</list>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oolongteainfo.com/tie-guan-yin/">
Tie Guan Yin</weblink></p>


<p>

<link xlink:label="zh-min-nan" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Thih-koan-im"></link>
<link xlink:label="de" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Tin kuan yin"></link>
<link xlink:label="es" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Tie Guan Yin"></link>
<link xlink:label="fr" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Tieguanyin"></link>
<link xlink:label="ko" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../ko/pages/001/196001.xml" xlink:title="철관음"></link>
<link xlink:label="ja" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../ja/pages/981/1057981.xml" xlink:title="鉄観音"></link>
<link xlink:label="pt" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Tieguanyin"></link>
<link xlink:label="ru" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Те Гуань Инь"></link>
<link xlink:label="zh-yue" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="鐵觀音"></link>
<link xlink:label="zh" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../zh/pages/352/56352.xml" xlink:title="铁观音"></link></p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
