<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] with modifications for the NTCIR Crosslink project on 21.03.2012 13:18:38[centos6] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Tsundere</title>
<id>2872586</id>
<revision>
<id>469437703</id>
<timestamp>2012-01-04T02:29:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>WhisperToMe</username>
<id>15708</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Moe</category>
<category>:Female stock characters in anime and manga</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="250px" src="Tsundere.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A typical example of tsundere characters
</caption>
</image>

 ( or , ) is a Japanese character development process that describes a person who is initially cold and even hostile towards another person before gradually showing their warm side over time. The word is derived from the terms , meaning to turn away in disgust, and  meaning to become 'lovey dovey'.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Originally found in Japanese bishōjo games, the word is now part of the otaku moe phenomenon, reaching into other media such as maid cafes, anime, manga, novels, and even mass media. The term was made popular in the visual novel <it>Kimi ga Nozomu Eien</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
Terminology</st>
<p>

<it>Tsundere</it> is considered a moe-inspiring character trait.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The concept has received increasing attention in Japan, with a tsundere cafe opened in Akihabara<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> and tsundere-themed products released (like Tomy Co.'s portable television set),<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> and the concept increasingly reflected in recent anime, from an extended discussion of the meaning of the concept and its origin on the Internet in <it>Lucky Star</it>'s Lucky Channel segment classifying the characters according to tsundere-ness. Another accepted definition of <it>tsundere</it> is a girl who has a combative attitude toward others but is also kind on the inside. She usually plays out as having an attitude toward the main character, usually a male, and often criticizing him in one way or another, but as the series progresses she eventually warms up to him or falls in love with him, though usually finds it very hard to admit it outright.</p>
<p>

Comiket organizer Koichi Ichikawa has described Lum Invader of <it>Urusei Yatsura</it> as being both the source of moe and the first tsundere;<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> figurine sculptor Bome has also cited Lum as an inspiration for his designs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Other anime &amp; manga featuring <it>tsundere</it> include <it>Love Hina</it>, <it>Naruto</it>,  and <it>Bakemonogatari</it>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> among many others. Some voice actors, such as Rie Kugimiya, specialize in portraying <it>tsundere</it>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> as with the character Taiga Aisaka in <it>Toradora!</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

<it>Tsundere</it> as a concept is not strictly limited to women, and is not strictly limited to manga or anime. The character Germany from the series <it></it> is portrayed as being <it>tsundere</it>, and is paired with a "lovable loser", Italy.  These characters represent their respective countries; thus the implication  is that Germany, the country, is <it>tsundere</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>  Tsundere role-play has become a common theme in maid cafés.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>


<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Glossary of anime and manga</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Yandere</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
