<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] with modifications for the NTCIR Crosslink project on 21.03.2012 13:18:37[centos6] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Traveler&apos;s cheque</title>
<id>1039570</id>
<revision>
<id>467004762</id>
<timestamp>2011-12-21T10:27:01Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Scott Sanchez</username>
<id>21150</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Travel gear</category>
<category>:Payment systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>


<image location="right" width="227px" src="20usdTravelersChequeNowSpent.jpg">
</image>

A <b>traveler's cheque</b> (also <b>traveller's cheque</b>, <b>travellers cheque</b>, <b>traveller's check</b> or <b>traveler's check</b>) is a preprinted, fixed-amount <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/494/1267494.xml">
cheque</link> designed to allow the person signing it to make an unconditional payment to someone else as a result of having paid the issuer for that privilege. 
<sec>
<st>
 Usage </st>
<p>

As traveler's cheques can usually be replaced if lost or stolen (if the owner still has the receipt issued with the purchase of the cheques showing the serial numbers allocated), they are often used by people on vacation in place of cash. </p>
<p>

Traveler's cheques are available in several currencies such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/338/18717338.xml">
U.S. dollars</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/846/101846.xml">
Canadian dollar</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/673/270673.xml">
Pounds sterling</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/392/34392.xml">
Japanese yen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/472/2279472.xml">
Chinese Yuan</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/472/9472.xml">
Euro</link>; denominations usually being 20, 50, or 100 (x100 for Yen) of whatever currency, and are usually sold in pads of five or ten cheques, e.g., 5 x €20 for €100. Traveler's cheques do not expire, so unused cheques can be kept by the purchaser to spend at any time in the future. The purchaser of a supply of traveler's cheques effectively gives an interest-free loan to the issuer, which is why it is common for banks to sell them "commission free" to their customers. The commission, where it is charged, is usually 1-2% of the total face value sold.</p>
<p>

In 2005, American Express released the <it>American Express Travelers Cheque Card</it>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/804/298804.xml">
stored-value card</link> that serves the same purposes as a traveler's cheque, but can be used in stores like a credit card. It however discontinued the card in October 2007.  A number of other financial companies went on to issue stored-value or <link>
pre-paid debit cards</link> containing several currencies that could be used like credit or debit cards at shops and at ATMs, mimicking the traveler's cheque in electronic form. One of the major examples is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/920/246920.xml">
Visa</link> TravelMoney card.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Traveler's cheques were first issued on 1 January 1772 by the <link>
London Credit Exchange Company</link> for use in ninety European cities,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> and in 1874 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/367/404367.xml">
Thomas Cook</link> was issuing '<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/925/4031925.xml">
circular note</link>s' that operated in the manner of traveler's cheques.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/512/326512.xml">
American Express</link> was the first company to develop a large-scale traveller's cheque system in 1891,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> and is still the largest issuer of traveler's cheques today by volume.</p>
<p>

American Express's introduction of traveler's cheques is traditionally attributed to employee <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/914/31457914.xml">
Marcellus Flemming Berry</link>, after company president <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/153/8787153.xml">
J.C. Fargo</link> had problems in smaller European cities obtaining funds with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/265/844265.xml">
letter of credit</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Terminology </st>
<p>

Legal terms for the parties to a traveler's cheque are the <b>obligor</b> or <b>issuer</b>, the organization that produces it; the <b>agent,</b> the bank or other place that sells it; the <b>purchaser,</b> the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/406/361406.xml">
natural person</link> who buys it, and the <b>payee,</b> the entity to whom the purchaser writes the cheque for goods and/or services. For purposes of clearance, the obligor is both <b>maker</b> and <b>drawee</b>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Use and acceptance </st>
<p>

Upon obtaining custody of a purchased supply of traveler's cheques, the purchaser should immediately write his or her <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/753/26753.xml">
signature</link> once upon each cheque, usually on the cheque's upper portion. The purchaser will also have received a receipt and some other documentation that should be kept in a safe place other than where he or she carries the cheques.</p>
<p>

When wanting to cash a traveler's cheque while making a purchase, the purchaser should, in the presence of the payee, date and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/411/17130411.xml">
countersign</link> the cheque in the indicated space, usually on the cheque's lower portion (if at a restaurant, it may be helpful to ask the waiter to watch and wait for this to be done).[https://www209.americanexpress.com/merchant/singlevoice/USEng/FrontServlet?request_type=navigate&amp;page=travelersChequesAndGiftCheques]</p>
<p>

Applicable change for a purchase transaction should be given in local currency as if the cheques were banknotes.</p>
<p>

Several travellers cheques have been created; the most widely accepted travellers cheques are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/581/9460581.xml">
Thomas Cook Group</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/512/326512.xml">
American Express</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Security concerns </st>
<p>

It is a reasonable security procedure for the payee to ask to inspect the purchaser's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/578/364578.xml">
picture ID</link>; a driver's license or passport should suffice, and doing so would most usefully be towards the end of comparing the purchaser's signature on the ID with those on the cheque. The best first step, however, that can be taken by any payee who has concerns about the validity of any traveler's cheque, is to contact the issuer directly; a negative finding by a third-party <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/720/1044720.xml">
cheque verification service</link> based on an ID check may merely indicate that the service has no record about the purchaser (to be expected, practically by definition, of many travelers), or at worst that he or she has been deemed incompetent to manage a personal chequing account (which would have no bearing on the validity of a traveller's cheque).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Black market </st>
<p>

One of the main advantages travellers cheques provide is the replacement if lost or stolen. This feature has also created a black market where swindlers buy travellers cheques, sell them at 50% of their value to other people (such as travellers) and falsely report their travellers cheque stolen with the company where the cheque has been obtained. As such, they get back the value of the travellers cheque and make 50% of the value as profit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Deposit and settlement </st>
<p>

A payee receiving a traveler's cheque should follow its normal procedures for depositing cheques into its bank account: usually, endorsement by stamp or signature and listing of the cheque and its amount on the deposit slip. The bank account will be credited with the amount of the cheque as with any other negotiable item submitted for clearance.</p>
<p>

In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/750/3434750.xml">
United States</link>, if the payee is equipped to process cheques electronically at point of sale (<it>see:</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/508/643508.xml">
Check 21 Act</link>), they should still take custody of the cheque and submit it to a financial institution, particularly to avoid any confusion on the part of the purchaser.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/407/1608407.xml">
Cashier's check</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/717/3027717.xml">
Certified check</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/475/3981475.xml">
Eurocheque</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/096/458096.xml">
Money order</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www10.americanexpress.com/sif/cda/page/0,1641,18540,00.asp?">
American Express Traveler's Cheques merchant site</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://usa.visa.com/personal/using_visa/visa_travelers_cheques.html">
Visa Travelers Cheques</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.travelex.co.uk/uk/personal/TC_visamcard.aspx">
Visa Interpayment Travellers Cheques</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.travelex.co.uk/uk/personal/TC_visamcard.aspx">
Thomas Cook Mastercard Travellers Cheques</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.travelex.co.uk/uk/personal/TC_visamcard.aspx">
Travelex Travellers Cheques</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<link xlink:label="cs" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Cestovní šek"></link>
<link xlink:label="de" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Reisescheck"></link>
<link xlink:label="fa" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="چک مسافرتی"></link>
<link xlink:label="fr" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Chèque de voyage"></link>
<link xlink:label="ko" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../ko/pages/221/317221.xml" xlink:title="여행자 수표"></link>
<link xlink:label="id" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Cek perjalanan"></link>
<link xlink:label="it" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Traveler's cheque"></link>
<link xlink:label="ja" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../ja/pages/791/159791.xml" xlink:title="トラベラーズチェック"></link>
<link xlink:label="no" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Reisesjekk"></link>
<link xlink:label="pl" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Czek podróżniczy"></link>
<link xlink:label="ru" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Дорожный чек"></link>
<link xlink:label="simple" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Traveler's cheque"></link>
<link xlink:label="sv" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Resecheck"></link>
<link xlink:label="zh" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../zh/pages/764/622764.xml" xlink:title="旅行支票"></link></p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
