<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] with modifications for the NTCIR Crosslink project on 21.03.2012 13:18:38[centos6] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Zhu Bajie</title>
<id>249299</id>
<revision>
<id>458962002</id>
<timestamp>2011-11-04T12:30:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>FoxBot</username>
<id>10254013</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Journey to the West characters</category>
<category>:Chinese mythology</category>
<category>:Fictional Buddhist monks</category>
<category>:Fictional monks</category>
<category>:Mythological pigs</category>
<category>:Fictional pigs</category>
<category>:Literary characters</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>



|s=
|p=Zhū Bājiè
|w=Chu1 Pa1-chieh4
|j=Zyu1 Baat3 Gaai3
|gan=Chu Pa̍t Kāi
|hiragana=ちょ はっかい
|romaji=Cho Hakkai
|hangul=저팔계
|rr=Jeo Palgye
|tha=ตือโป๊ยก่าย
|rtgs=Tue Poikai (from a Hokkian pronunciation of "Zhu Bajie")
|vie=Trư Bát Giới
|altname=Zhu Wuneng
|t2=
|s2=
|p2=Zhū Wùnéng
|w2=Chu1 Wu4-neng2
|j2=Zyu1 Ng6 Nang4
}}
<b>Zhu Bajie</b>, also named <b>Zhu Wuneng</b>, is one of the three helpers of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/372/232372.xml">
Xuanzang</link> in the classic Chinese novel <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/367/232367.xml">
Journey to the West</link></it>. He is called "<b>Pigsy</b>" or "Pig" in many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/916/8569916.xml">
English</link> versions of the story.<p>

Zhu Bajie is a complex and developed character in the novel.  He looks like a terrible monster, part <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/482/682482.xml">
human</link> and part <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/142/25142.xml">
pig</link>, who often gets himself and his companions into trouble through his laziness, gluttony, and propensity for lusting after pretty women. He is jealous of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/503/231503.xml">
Sun Wukong</link> and always tries to bring him down. </p>
<p>

His Buddhist name "Zhu Wuneng", given by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/968/3968.xml">
Bodhisattva</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/063/17063.xml">
Guanyin</link>, means "pig (reincarnated) who is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/526/237526.xml">
aware of</link> ability," or "pig who rises to power", a reference to the fact that he values himself so much as to forget his own grisly appearance. Xuanzang gave him the nickname <it>Bājiè</it> which means "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/780/24780.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Eight+Precepts%22])">
eight restraints, or eight commandments</link>" to remind him of his Buddhist diet. </p>
<p>

In the original Chinese novel, he is often called <it>dāizi</it> (呆子), meaning "idiot".  Sun Wukong, Xuanzang and even the author consistently refers to him as "the idiot" over the course of the story.  Bodhisattvas and other heavenly beings usually refer to him as "Heavenly Tumbleweed", his former name when he was a heavenly marshal.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Character </st>
<p>

Zhu Bajie originally held the title of <it>Tiānpéng Yuánshuài</it> (天蓬元帅; lit. "Marshal Canopy"), commander-in-chief of 80,000 Heavenly Navy Soldiers. He was later banished, however, for misbehaviour.  At a party organized for all the significant figures in Heaven, Bajie saw the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/971/369971.xml">
Goddess of the Moon</link> for the first time and was captivated by her beauty. Following a drunken attempt to get close to her, she reported this to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/285/312285.xml">
Jade Emperor</link> and thus he was banished to Earth. In popular retellings, Zhu Bajie was sentenced to a thousand lives where each life would end in a love tragedy. In some retellings of the story, his banishment is linked to Sun Wukong's downfall. In any case, he was exiled from Heaven and sent to be reincarnated on Earth, where by mishap he fell into a pig well and was reborn as a man-eating pig-monster known as <it>Zhū Gāngliè</it> (the "strong-maned pig").</p>
<p>

In the earlier portions of <it>Journey to the West</it>, Wukong and Xuanzang come to Gao village and find that a daughter of the village elder had been kidnapped and the abductor left a note demanding marriage.  In some versions of the story Bajie has convinced the elder to allow him to marry the daughter based on his ability to do large amounts of hard work due to his prodigious strength.  The elder recants when he discovers that although Zhu Bajie manages to do quite a lot of work in the fields he manages to eat so much that the farm is losing money anyway.  After some investigations, Wukong found out that Bajie was the "villain" behind this. He fought with Wukong, but ended the fight when he learned that Wukong was a disciple of Xuanzang, and that he had also been recruited by Guanyin to join their pilgrimage and make atonements for his past sins.</p>
<p>

Like his fellow disciples, Bajie has supernatural powers.  He is capable of 36 transformations, and like his fellow disciple, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/102/708102.xml">
Sha Wujing</link>, his combat skills underwater are superior to that of Wukong.  The novel makes use of constant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/455/1947455.xml">
alchemical</link> imagery and Bajie is most closely linked to the Wood element, as seen by another one of his nicknames, <it>Mùmǔ</it> (木母, "Wood-Mother").</p>
<p>

At the end of the novel, most of Bajie's fellow pilgrims achieve enlightenment and become <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/976/174976.xml">
buddhas</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/250/21996250.xml">
arhat</link>s, but he does not; although much improved, he is still too much a creature of his base desires. He is instead rewarded for his part in the pilgrimage's success with a job as "Cleanser of the Altars" and all the leftovers he can eat. However, his actual rank in relation to the others is unclear.</p>
<p>

As a weapon, he wields a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/299/249299.xml">
jiǔchǐ-dīngpá</link>, a nine-tooth (<it>jiǔchǐ</it>) iron muck-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/601/1157601.xml">
rake</link> (<it>dīngpá</it>) from Heaven that weighs roughly 5,048 kilos (or roughly 11,129 pounds).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Nine-toothed rake</st>
<p>

The nine-toothed rake (Traditional Chinese: 九齒釘耙; Simplified Chinese: 九齿钉耙; pinyin: jiǔchǐdīngpá; literally Nine-Tooth Spike-Rake) is the primary weapon of Zhu Bajie. This phrase depicts the first point in which Bajie's legendary nine-toothed rake had been used:</p>
<p>

The fierce and murderous ogre;
Huian, imposing and able.
The iron staff could pulverize the heart;
The rake struck at the face.
The dust thrown up darkened Heaven and Earth;
The flying sand and stones startled gods and ghouls.
The nine−toothed rake
Gleamed and flashed
As its pair of rings resounded;
The lone staff
Was ominously black
As it whirled in its owner's hands.
One was the heir of a Heavenly King,
One defended the Law on Potaraka Island.
The other was an evil fiend in a mountain cave.
In their battle for mastery,
None knew who the winner would be.</p>
<p>

In another passage, Pig tells of his legendary rake while battling against Sun Wukong:</p>
<p>

This was refined from divine ice−iron,
Polished till it gleamed dazzling white,
Hammered by Lord Lao Zi himself,
While Ying Huo fed the fire with coal−dust.
The Five Emperors of the Five Regions applied their minds to it,
The Six Dings and Six jias went to great efforts.
They made nine teeth of jade,
Cast a pair of golden rings to hang beneath them,
Decorated the body with the Six Bright Shiners and the Five planets,
Designed it in accordance with the Four Seasons and the Eight Divisions.
The length of top and bottom match Heaven and Earth.
Positive and Negative were to left and right, dividing the sun and moon.
The Six Divine Generals of the Oracular Lines are there, following the Heavenly Code;
The constellations of the Eight Trigrams are set out in order.
It was named the Supremely Precious Gold−imbued Rake,
And served to guard the gates of the Jade Emperor's palace.
As I had become a great Immortal,
I now enjoyed eternal life,
And was commissioned as Marshal Tian Peng,</p>
<p>

With this rake to mark my imperial office.
When I raise it, fire and light stream forth;
When I lower it, a snowy blizzard blows.
It terrifies the Heavenly Generals,
And makes the King of Hell too quake with fear.
There is no other weapon matching it on Earth,
Nor iron to rival it throughout the world.
It changes into anything I like,
And leaps about whenever I say the spell.
For many a year I've carried it around,
Keeping it with me every single day.
I will not put it down even to eat,
Nor do I when I sleep at night.
I took it with me to the Peach Banquet,
And carried it into the celestial court.
When I sinned my sin in drunken pride,
I used it to force compliance with my evil will.
When Heaven sent me down to the mortal dust,
I committed all kinds of wickedness down here.
I used to devour people in this cave,
Until I fell in love and married in Gao Village.
This rake has plunged beneath the sea to stir up dragons,
And climbed high mountains to smash up tigers' dens.
No other blade is worth a mention
Besides my rake, the sharpest weapon ever.
To win a fight with it requires no effort;</p>
<p>

Of course it always brings me glory.
Even if you have an iron brain in a brazen head and a body of steel,
This rake will scatter your souls and send your spirit flying.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../pages/799/23516799.xml">
Journey to the West in popular culture</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>


</p>

<p>

<link xlink:label="bo" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="ཀྲུའུ་པའ་ཅེད།"></link>
<link xlink:label="ca" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Zhu Bajie"></link>
<link xlink:label="fr" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Zhu Bajie"></link>
<link xlink:label="ko" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../ko/pages/802/319802.xml" xlink:title="저팔계"></link>
<link xlink:label="it" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Zhu Wuneng"></link>
<link xlink:label="ja" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../ja/pages/543/9543.xml" xlink:title="猪八戒"></link>
<link xlink:label="pl" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Zhu Bajie"></link>
<link xlink:label="ru" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Чжу Бацзе"></link>
<link xlink:label="th" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="ตือโป๊ยก่าย"></link>
<link xlink:label="vi" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="Trư Bát Giới"></link>
<link xlink:label="zh-yue" xlink:type="none" xlink:title="豬八戒"></link>
<link xlink:label="zh" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../../../zh/pages/648/24648.xml" xlink:title="猪八戒"></link></p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
