<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 93 $ on 27.02.2011 08:46:19[cl1n033] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Kimchi</title>
<id>178952</id>
<revision>
<id>376673120</id>
<timestamp>2010-08-02T00:14:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Qwyrxian</username>
<id>1414995</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Korean words and phrases</category>
<category>:Kimchi</category>
<category>:National dishes</category>
<category>:Korean cuisine</category>
<category>:Fermented foods</category>
<category>:Pickles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>



<b>Kimchi</b> (김치; , ), also spelled <b>gimchi</b>, <b>kimchee</b>, or <b>kim chee</b>, is a traditional Korean dish, made of vegetables with varied seasonings. Many varieties of kimchi are fermented although unfermented varieties also exist.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.  There are hundreds of varieties of kimchi, made with a main vegetable ingredient such as napa cabbage, radish, green onion or cucumber.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Kimchi is the most common banchan, or side dish, in Korean cuisine. Kimchi is also a main ingredient for many popular Korean dishes such as kimchi stew (김치찌개; <it>kimchi jjigae</it>), kimchi soup (김칫국; kimchi gook), and kimchi fried rice (김치볶음밥; <it>kimchi bokkeumbap</it>).<p>

Kimchi is so ubiquitous to Korean cuisine that the Korea Aerospace Research Institute (KARI) developed space kimchi to accompany the first Korean astronaut to the Russian-manned space ship Soyuz.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="150px" src="Korea-Kimchi-Ancient.form-Museum-01.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Ancient Kimchi
</caption>
</image>

The oldest references to kimchi can be found from 2600 to 3000 years ago.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> The first text-written evidence of its existence can be found in the first Chinese poetry book, <it>Shi Jing</it> (). In this book, kimchi was referred to as <it>jeo</it> (菹). The term <it>ji</it> was used until the pre-modern terms <it>chimchae</it> (hanja: 沈菜, lit. soaked vegetables), <it>dimchae</it>, and <it>timchae</it> were adopted in the period of the Three Kingdoms of Korea.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> The word then was modified into <it>jimchi</it>, and is currently <it>kimchi</it>. 
Early kimchi was made of cabbage and beef stock only. Red chili, a New World vegetable not found in Korea before European contact with the Americas, was added to kimchi recipes some time after 1500.  Red chili pepper flakes are now used as the main ingredient for spice and source of heat for many varieties of kimchi. In the twelfth century other spices, creating flavors such as sweet and sour, and colors, such as white and orange, were added.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Main ingredients</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Korean.Folk.Village-Minsokchon-02.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Chili peppers drying for kimchi
</caption>
</image>

Kimchi varieties are determined by the main vegetable ingredients and the mix of seasonings used to flavor the kimchi. The most popular type of kimchi is the baechu (also known as Chinese cabbage) variety but there are many regional and seasonal varieties. Popular variants include <it>ggakdugi</it> which is a kimchi made with cubed radish, <it>pa-kimchi</it> (made with scallions), <it>chonggak-kimchi</it> and <it>oisobagi</it> (hangul: 오이소박이), a cucumber kimchi with hot and spicy seasoning; <it>gat-kimchi</it> (hangul: 갓김치), <it>boochoo-kimchi</it> (hangul: 부추김치),  <it>Kkaennip</it> (hangul: 깻잎) kimchi features layers of perilla and other spices.</p>
<p>

The Kimchi Field Museum in Seoul has documented 187 historic and current varieties of kimchi. Although the most common seasonings include brine, scallions and spices, ingredients can be replaced or added depending on the type of kimchi being made. Common seasonings also include ginger, chopped radish, garlic, <it>saeujeot</it> (hangul: 새우젓), and <it>aekjeot</it> (hangul: 액젓, fish sauce).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Kimchi varieties</st>
<p>

Image:Korean.cuisine-Banchan-02.jpg|thumb|left|<it>Dongchimi</it>, <it>gulgimchi</it> (kimchi with additional oyster) and other banchan]]
Kimchi can be categorized by main ingredients, regions or seasons. Korea's northern and southern sections have a considerable temperature difference.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> Northern regions tend to have longer winters compared to the southern regions of Korea. </p>
<p>

Kimchi from the northern parts of Korea tend to have less salt as well as less red chilli and usually do not have brined seafood for seasoning. Northern kimchi often has a watery consistency. Kimchi made in the southern parts of Korea, such as Jeolla-do and Gyeongsang-do, uses salt, chili peppers and <it>myeolchijeot</it> (hangul: 멸치젓, brined anchovy allowed to ferment) or <it>saeujeot</it> (hangul: 새우젓, brined shrimp allowed to ferment), <it>myeolchiaekjeot</it> (Hangul: 멸치액젓, "kkanariaekjeot" 까나리액젓, liquid anchovy jeot, similar to fish sauce used in Southeast Asia, but thicker). In the Seoul area <it>saeujeot</it> is preferred. </p>
<p>

<it>Saeujeot</it> (hangul: 새우젓) or <it>meyolchijeot</it> is not added to the kimchi spice-seasoning mixture, but is simmered to reduce odors, eliminate tannic flavor and fats, and then is mixed with a thickener made of rice or wheat starch (Hangul: 풀). This technique has been falling into disuse for the past forty years.</p>
<p>

Other brined <it>jeot</it> can be used, but are no longer common as modern commercialization has made <it>aekjeot</it> (액젓; either <it>myeolchijeot</it> or <it>saeujeot</it>) more affordable and convenient.</p>
<p>

White kimchi (<it>baek kimchi</it>) is baechu seasoned without chili pepper and is neither red in color nor spicy. White radish kimchi (<it>dongchimi</it>) is another example of a popular kimchi that is not spicy. The watery white kimchi varieties are a popular ingredient in a number of dishes such as cold noodles in <it>dongchimi</it> brine (<it>dongchimi guksu</it>) and are eaten widely during the summer months.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
By region</st>
<p>

Image:Kimchi jar.JPG|thumb|Traditional jars used for storing kimchi, gochujang, doenjang, soy sauce and other pickled banchan]]
This regional classification dates back to 1960s and contains plenty of historical facts, but the current kimchi-making trends in Korea are generally different from those mentioned below.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Hamgyeong-do</it> (Upper Northeast)</entry>
</list>

Due to its proximity to the ocean, people in this particular region use fresh fish and oysters to season their kimchi.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Hwanghae-do</it> (Midwest)</entry>
</list>

The taste of kimchi in Hwanghae-do can be best described as "moderate" — not bland but not overly spicy. Most kimchi from this region has less color since red chili flakes are not used. The typical kimchi for Hwanghae-do is called pumpkin kimchi (<it>bundi</it>).
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Korean.food-kimchi-02.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<it>Kimchi Buchingae''</it>
</caption>
</image>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Gyeonggi-do</it> (Lower Midwest of Hwanghae-do) Gyeonggi-do kimchi is known for its eye-catching decorations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Chungcheong-do</it> (Between Gyeonggi-do and Jeolla-do)</entry>
</list>

Instead of using fermented fish, people in the region rely on salt and fermentation to make savory kimchi. Chungcheong-do is known for the greatest varieties of kimchi.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Gangwon-do (South Korea)/Kangwon-do (North Korea)</it> (Mideast)</entry>
</list>

In Gangwon-do, kimchi is stored for longer periods of time. Unlike other coastal regions in Korea, kimchi in this area does not contain much salted fish.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Jeolla-do</it> (Lower Southwest)</entry>
</list>

Salted yellow corvine and salted butterfish are used in this region to create different seasonings for kimchi. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Gyeongsang-do</it> (Lower Southeast)</entry>
</list>

This region is famous for salty and spicy flavors in its dishes and their kimchi is no exception. The most common seasoning components includes myeolchijeot (멸치젓) which produce a briny and savory flavor.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
By season</st>
<p>

Different types of kimchi were traditionally made at different times of year, based on when various vegetable were in season and also to take advantage of hot and cold seasons before the era of refrigeration. Although the advent of modern refrigeration —- including kimchi refrigerators specifically designed with precise controls to keep different varieties of kimchi at optimal temperatures at various stages of fermentation —- has made this seasonality unnecessary, Koreans continue to consume kimchi according to traditional seasonal preferences.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> </p>
<p>

Image:Korean.cuisine-Chonggak.kimchi-01.jpg|thumb|right|<it>Chonggak kimchi</it>]]
Image:Korean-Dongchimi-01.jpg|thumb|<it>Dongchimi (동치미)</it> is largely eaten during winter.]]
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Spring </entry>
</list>

Traditionally, after a long period of consuming <it>gimjang kimchi</it> (hangul: 김장김치) during the winter, fresh potherbs and vegetables were popular for making kimchi. These kinds of kimchi were not fermented or even stored for long periods of time but were consumed fresh.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Summer</entry>
</list>

Young summer radishes and cucumbers are popular summer vegetables made into kimchi, <it>yeolmu kimchi</it> (hangul: 열무김치) which is eaten in several bites. Brined fish or shellfish can be added and freshly ground dried chili peppers are often used.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Autumn</entry>
</list>

<it>Baechu kimchi</it> is the most common type of kimchi in the fall. It is prepared by inserting blended stuffing materials, called <it>sok</it> (literally meaning <it>inside</it>), between layers of salted leaves of uncut, whole Napa cabbage (also widely called Chinese cabbage). The ingredients of <it>sok</it> (hangul: 속) can vary, depending on the different regions and weather conditions. Generally, <it>baechoo kimchi</it> used to have a strong salty flavor until the late 1960s when a large amount of <it>myeolchijeot</it> or <it>saeujeot</it> had been used. Since the advent of <it>aekjeot</it> (액젓, Korean fish sauce) in the early 1970s, however, low-sodium kimchi is preferably made both at homes and at factories.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Winter</entry>
</list>

Traditionally, the greatest varieties of kimchi were available during the winter. In preparation for the long winter months, many types of kimjang kimchi (hangul: 김장 김치) were prepared in early winter and stored in the ground in large kimchi pots. Modern kimchi refrigerators offering precise temperature controls are used to store kimjang kimchi. November and December are traditionally when people begin to make kimchi; women often gather together in each others' homes to help with winter kimchi preparations. White kimchi (<it>baek kimchi</it>) is a popular kimchi to make during the wintertime. "Baechu kimchi" is made with salted baechu (a type of Chinese cabbage) filled with thin strips of radish, parsley, pine nuts, pears, chestnuts, shredded red pepper, manna lichen (석이버섯), garlic, and ginger.</p>

</ss2>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Nutrition and health</st>
<p>

Kimchi is made of various vegetables and contains a high concentration of dietary fiber, while being low in calories. One serving also provides up to 80% of the daily recommended amount of vitamin C and carotene. Most types of kimchi contain onions, garlic, and peppers, all of which are salutary. The vegetables being made into kimchi also contribute to the overall nutritional value. Kimchi is rich in vitamin A, thiamine (B1), riboflavin (B2), calcium, and iron,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> and contains a number of lactic acid bacteria, among those the typical species <it>Lactobacillus kimchii</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>  The magazine <it>Health</it> named kimchi in its list of top five "World's Healthiest Foods" for being rich in vitamins, aiding digestion, and even possibly reducing cancer growth.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>
Image:Korean stew-Kimchi jjigae-05.jpg|thumb|<it>Kimchi jjigae</it>. A popular stew made with kimchi, it is commonly cooked with kimchi, fresh vegetables and pork or tuna although countless variants exist.]]</p>
<p>

One study conducted by Seoul National University claimed that chickens infected with the H5N1 virus, also called avian flu, recovered after eating food containing the same bacteria found in kimchi.  During the 2003 SARS outbreak in Asia, many people even believed that kimchi could protect against infection, although there was no scientific evidence to support this belief.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> However, in May 2009, the Korea Food Research Institute, Korea’s state food research organization, said they had conducted a larger study on 200 chickens, which supported the theory that it boosts chickens' immunity to the virus.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<caption>
<b>Nutritional composition of typical kimchi</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></caption>
<header>
Nutrients</header>
<header>
per 100 g *</header>
<header>
Nutrients</header>
<header>
per 100 g</header>
<row>
<col>
Food energy</col>
<col>
32 kcal</col>
<col>
Moisture</col>
<col>
88.4 g</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Crude protein</col>
<col>
2.0 g</col>
<col>
Crude Lipid</col>
<col>
0.6 g</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Total sugar</col>
<col>
1.3 g</col>
<col>
Crude fiber</col>
<col>
1.2 g</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Crude ash</col>
<col>
0.5 g</col>
<col>
Calcium</col>
<col>
45&nbsp;mg</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Phosphorus</col>
<col>
28&nbsp;mg</col>
<col>
Vitamin A</col>
<col>
492 IU</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Vitamin B1</col>
<col>
0.03&nbsp;mg</col>
<col>
Vitamin B2</col>
<col>
0.06&nbsp;mg</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Niacin</col>
<col>
2.1&nbsp;mg</col>
<col>
Vitamin C</col>
<col>
21&nbsp;mg</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

* Per 100 g of edible portion.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
1996 Kimchi dispute</st>
<p>


In 1996, Japan manufacturers proposed making kimchi the official Atlanta Olympics food, and decided to export Japanese made kimuchi (キムチ, the Japanese pronunciation of kimchi) to other countries. Korea argued that Japanese kimuchi was substantially different than kimchi (in particular, that it was not fermented), and that it therefore should not be labeled kimchi. Korea sought recognition from the Codex Alimentarius, an organization associated with the World Health Organization to define kimchi in ways similar to traditional Korean production methods. In 2001, the Codex Alimentarius adopted a standard for kimchi that largely reflected Korean production practices.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Gallery</st>




</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jangajji</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jeotgal</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Torshi</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sauerkraut</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pao cai</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Korean cuisine</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Foods containing tyramine</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

List of English words of Korean origin</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fermentation (food)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>



<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://english.visitkorea.or.kr/enu/SI/SI_EN_3_4_8_2.jsp">
The A to Z's of Kimchi</weblink> - The Official Korea Tourism Guide Site</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kimchi.or.kr/eng/index.html">
Korean traditional kimchi</weblink> site sponsored by the Korean Agro-Fisheries Trade Corp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://english.visitkorea.or.kr/enu/FO/FO_EN_6_1_2_1.jsp">
Kimchi &amp;gt; History</weblink> at the Korea Tourism Organization official site</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://kimchi.kfri.re.kr/html_en/html/kimchi_01.htm">
Korea Food Research Institute</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
