<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] with modifications for the NTCIR Crosslink project on 21.03.2012 13:18:37[centos6] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Crown Prince Sado</title>
<id>4898073</id>
<revision>
<id>469397571</id>
<timestamp>2012-01-03T21:32:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>XLinkBot</username>
<id>6163802</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Heirs apparent who never acceded</category>
<category>:1735 births</category>
<category>:18th-century Korean people</category>
<category>:House of Yi</category>
<category>:1762 deaths</category>
<category>:Joseon Dynasty people</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<p>

<b>Crown Prince Sado</b> (1735&ndash;1762) was born as the second son of the Korean king Yeongjo of Joseon. Because his older brother, Prince Hyojang, had died young, in 1728, Prince Sado was born the royal heir. However, it had been reported to his father that he was mentally ill, wantonly killed people, and was very erratic. This was a disappointment to his father, and with the consent of Lady Yi, Yeongjo finally ordered him to be sealed alive in a large rice chest, where he died within eight days. His son Yi San became King Jeongjo in 1776, after King Yeongjo's death. </p>
<p>

In the 19th century there were rumors that Prince Sado had not been mentally ill, but had been framed; however, these rumors are contradicted by the <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> (한중록) of Prince Sado's wife, Queen Heongyeong (also known as Lady Hyegyeong). It is still disputable up to now if his death was a retribution for his actual misconduct or he was just victimized by the conspiracy of his political opponents.</p>
<p>

Crown Prince Sado was buried on Mr Baebongsan in Yangju. In 1789, his body was moved by his son King Jeongjo to its current location, then called Hyeollyungwon near Suwon, 30 kilometres south of Seoul. During 1794-1796, Hwaseong Fortress was built and dedicated to honor this tomb.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  In 1816, Lady Hyegyeong died and was buried with her husband. In 1899, Prince Sado and Lady Hyegyeong were posthumously elevated in status and given the titles Emperor Yangjo and Empress Heonyeong. Their tomb was upgraded accordingly and renamed Yungneung.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Family</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Father: King Yeongjo (영조)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mother: Royal Noble Consort Yeong of the Jeoneui Yi clan (영빈 이씨, 1696–August 23, 1764)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Consorts:</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Queen Heongyeong of the Poongsan Hong clan (헌경왕후 홍씨, 1735–1815)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Royal Noble Consort Suk of the Im clan (숙빈 임씨)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Royal Noble Consort Gyeong of the Park clan (경빈 박씨)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Issue:</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Prince Successor Uiso (의소세자, 1750–1752), 1st Son of Queen Heongyeong of the Hong clan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Royal Prince Successor Descendant (왕세손, 1752–1800), 2nd Son of Queen Heongyeong of the Hong clan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Prince Euneon (은언군, 1754–1801), 1st Son of Royal Noble Consort Suk of the Im clan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Prince Eunshin (은신군, 1755–1771), 2nd Son of Royal Noble Consort Suk of the Im clan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Prince Eunjeon (은전군, 1759–1778), Only Son of Royal Noble Consort Gyeong of the Park clan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Princess Cheongyeon (청연공주), 1st Daughter of Queen Heongyeong of the Hong clan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Princess Cheongseon (청선공주, 1756–1802), 2nd Daughter of Queen Heongyeong of the Hong clan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Princess Cheonggeun (청근옹주, 1758–1792), Only Daughter of Royal Noble Consort Gyeong of the Park clan.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
His full posthumous name</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Prince Successor Sado Sudeok Dongyeong Hongin Gyeongji Jangryun Ryungbeom Kimyeong Changhyu Jangheon</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 사도수덕돈경홍인경지장륜륭범기명창휴장헌세자</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 思悼綏德敦慶弘仁景祉章倫隆範基命彰休莊獻世子</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
His imperial posthumous name</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ui Emperor Jangjo</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 장조의황제</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 莊祖懿皇帝</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ancestry</st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Lady Hyegyeong wrote an autobiography <it>The Memoirs of Lady Hyegyeong (한중록, 閑中錄)</it>, detailing her life as the ill-fated Crown Princess of Korea.</entry>
<entry id="2">
</entry>
<entry id="3">
</entry>
<entry id="4">
Daughter of Yi Yoo Beon (이유번) and Madame Gim</entry>
<entry id="5">
Also known as Lady Seonhui</entry>
<entry id="6">
Daughter of Hong Bong-han (홍봉한) (great-great-grandson of Princess JeongMyoung (1603-1685) and Lady Yi of the Hansun Yi clan; also called "Lady Hyegyeong" (혜경궁), the only legitimate daughter of King Seonjo)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xs4all.nl/~monarchs/madmonarchs/sado/sado_bio.htm">
Biography of Crown Prince Sado of Korea</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
