<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 93 $ on 26.02.2011 07:35:18[cl1n033] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Ivory</title>
<id>15165</id>
<revision>
<id>375893859</id>
<timestamp>2010-07-28T11:12:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ivorymammoth</username>
<id>5933020</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Ivory</category>
<category>:Sculpture materials</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>


<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Ivory_tusk_160_cm.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

one edge of Mammoth Ivory big tusk hand carved with Assorted Gods
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Ivory_decoration.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

An elaborately carved ivory decoration
</caption>
</image>

File:Decorated ivory.JPG|thumb|right|An ivory decoration in Sa'dabad Palace]]
File:AGMA Ivory Pyxis with Griffins Attacking Stags.jpg|thumb|Ancient Greek ivory pyxis with griffins attacking stags. Late 15th century BCE, Ancient Agora Museum in Athens]]
File:The Bull Leaper Knossos 1500BC.jpg|thumb|The Bull Leaper, an ivory figurine from the palace of Knossos, Crete, 15th century BCE]]</p>
<p>

<b>Ivory</b> is formed from dentine and constitutes the bulk of the teeth and tusks of animals such as the elephant, hippopotamus, walrus, mammoth and narwhal.</p>
<p>

The word "ivory" was traditionally applied to the tusks of elephants; the word is ultimately from Ancient Egyptian <it>âb, âbu</it> "elephant", through the Latin <it>ebor-</it> or <it>ebur</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

The use and trade of ivory has become controversial as its harvesting, which often involves killing elephants solely for their tusks, has contributed to declining populations in some areas.  Many organizations, including the United Nations, have banned the ivory trade, and many governments prohibit harvesting.  Poaching and smuggling in violation of such bans is a problem in some places. </p>
<p>

Ivory has availed itself to many ornamental and practical uses. Prior to the introduction of plastics, it was used for billiard balls, piano keys, Scottish bagpipes, buttons and a wide range of ornamental items. Synthetic substitutes for ivory have been developed. Plastics have been viewed by piano purists as an inferior ivory substitute on piano keys, although other recently developed materials more closely resemble the feel of real ivory. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Structure </st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Mammoth_ivory_hg.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Section through the ivory tooth of a mammoth
</caption>
</image>

<image width="180px" src="Porphyrogenetus.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Ivory has been a most prestigious material for carving.
</caption>
</image>

File:Ivory cover of the Lorsch Gospels, c. 810, Carolingian, Victoria and Albert Museum.jpg|thumb|right|180px|Ivory cover of the Codex Aureus of Lorsch, c. 810, Carolingian dynasty, Victoria and Albert Museum]]
The chemical structure of the teeth and tusks of mammals is the same regardless of the species of origin. The trade in certain teeth and tusks other than elephant is well established and widespread, therefore "ivory" can correctly be used to describe any mammalian teeth or tusks of commercial interest which is large enough to be carved or scrimshawed.</p>
<p>

Both the Greek and Roman civilizations used large quantities of ivory to make high value works of art, precious religious objects, and decorative boxes for costly objects. Ivory was often used to form the white of the eyes of statues.</p>
<p>

The Syrian and North African flacid elephant populations were reduced to extinction, probably due to the demand for ivory in the Classical world.</p>
<p>

The Chinese have long valued ivory for both art and utilitarian objects. Early reference to the Chinese export of ivory is recorded after the Chinese explorer Zhang Qian ventured to the west to form alliances to enable for the eventual free movement of Chinese goods to the west; as early as the first century BC, ivory was moved along the Northern Silk Road for consumption by western nations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Southeast Asian kingdoms included tusks of the Indian elephant in their annual tribute caravans to China. Chinese craftsmen carved ivory to make everything from images of deities to the pipe-stems and end-pieces of opium pipes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  </p>
<p>

The Indianized Buddhist cultures of Southeast Asia, including Myanmar (Burma), Thailand, Laos and Cambodia traditionally harvested ivory from their domesticated elephants. Ivory was prized for containers due to its ability to keep an airtight seal. Ivory was also commonly carved into elaborate seals utilized by officials to "sign" documents and decrees by stamping them with their unique official seal.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

In Southeast Asian countries where Muslim Malay peoples live, such as Malaysia, Indonesia and the Philippines, ivory was the material of choice for making the handles of magical kris daggers. In the Philippines, ivory was also used to craft the faces and hands of Catholic icons and images of saints.</p>
<p>

Tooth and tusk ivory can be carved into a vast variety of shapes and objects. A small example of modern carved ivory objects are small statuary such as okimono, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://netsukes.org">
netsuke</weblink>]]s, jewelry, flatware handles, furniture inlays, and piano keys. Additionally, warthog tusks, and teeth from sperm whales, orcas and hippos can also be scrimshawed or superficially carved, thus retaining their morphologically recognizable shapes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Consumption before plastics </st>

<p>

Before plastics were invented, ivory was important for cutlery handles, musical instruments, billiard balls, and many other items. It is estimated that consumption in Great Britain alone in 1831 amounted to the deaths of nearly 4,000 elephants. Ivory can be taken from dead animals — Russians dug up tusks from extinct mammoths — however most ivory came from elephants who were killed for their tusks. Other animals which are now endangered were also preyed upon, for example, hippos, which have very hard white ivory prized for making artificial teeth.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Availability </st>
<p>

File:Ivory trade.jpg|thumb|upright|Men with ivory tusks, Dar es Salaam, c.&nbsp;1900.]]
Owing to the rapid decline in the populations of the animals that produce it, the importation and sale of ivory in many countries is banned or severely restricted. Much of the decline in population is due to poachers during and before the 1980s. Since the United Nations placed a nine-year moratorium on ivory in 1989, there have been ups and downs in elephant populations as bans have been lifted for poorer nations with large elephant populations. Many African countries&mdash;including Zimbabwe, Zambia, Namibia, and Botswana&mdash;claim that the ivory trade is necessary both to stimulate their economies and to cull large populations of elephants, which are allegedly harming the environment.</p>
<p>

In 2007 eBay, under pressure from the International Fund for Animal Welfare, banned all international sales of elephant-ivory products. The decision came after several mass slaughters of African elephants, most notably the 2006 Zakouma elephant slaughter in Chad. The IFAW found that up to 90% of the elephant-ivory transactions on Ebay violated their own wildlife policies and could potentially be illegal.  In October 2008, eBay expanded the ban, disallowing any sales of ivory on eBay.</p>
<p>

In 2002 the United Nations partially lifted the ban on ivory trade, allowing a few countries to export certain amounts of ivory. Six years later, the UN-backed Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species granted China and Japan permission to import elephant ivory from African government stockpiles in a one-time auction. Approximately 44 tons of ivory from Botswana, 9 tons from Namibia, 51 tons from South Africa, and 4 tons from Zimbabwe were sold.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

Kenya emerged as the main critic of these one-off sales. The country saw its elephant populations plummet in the decade preceding the 1989 ban, and claims that legalizing ivory trade anywhere in Africa will endanger elephants everywhere in Africa as poachers would attempt to launder their illegal ivory with legal stockpiles. In 2010, Kenya and 22 allies proposed a 20-year moratorium in ivory trade at a special session of the Doha Development Round.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Alternative sources</st>
<p>

Trade in the ivory from the tusks of dead mammoths has occurred for 300 years and continues to be legal. Mammoth ivory is used today to make handcrafted knives and similar implements. Mammoth ivory is rare and costly, because mammoths have been extinct for millennia and scientists loathe to sell museum-worthy specimens in pieces, but this trade does not threaten any living species.</p>
<p>

A species of hard nut is gaining popularity as a replacement for ivory, although its size limits its usability. It is sometimes called <b>vegetable ivory</b>, or tagua, and is the seed endosperm of the ivory nut palm commonly found in coastal rainforests of Ecuador, Peru and Colombia.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ivory carving</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ivory trade</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Vegetable ivory</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Walrus ivory</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
The New Shorter Oxford English Dictionary (Oxford 1993), entry for "ivory."</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.megalithic.co.uk/article.php?sid=18006">
C.Michael Hogan,<it>Silk Road, North China</it>, The Megalithic Portal, ed. A. Burnham</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
Martin, Steven. <it>The Art of Opium Antiques</it>. (2007). Silkworm Books, Chiang Mai</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asianart.com/articles/thai-ivory/index.html">
http://www.asianart.com/articles/thai-ivory/index.html</weblink> <it>Ivory Carving in Thailand</it> Retrieved on 08-30-07</entry>
<entry id="5">
 Vol I, pages 929-930.</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.economist.com/world/international/displayStory.cfm?source=hptextfeature&amp;story_id=11751304">
Ivory sales | Round the horn | Economist.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
{http://www.afrol.com/articles/31435 "Conservationists cry foul of Southern Africa ivory auction"} Afrol News, accessed 22 January 2009}</entry>
<entry id="8">
</entry>
<entry id="9">
</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>


<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.traffic.org/display/Search?searchQuery=ivory&amp;moduleId=1805190">
TRAFFIC reports on the ivory trade including those on ETIS (Elephant Trade Information System), prepared on behalf of CITES</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.internationalivorysociety.com">
The International Ivory Society</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://whistlemuseum.com/2009/03/21/french-woman-seem-to-be-very-popular-upon-demand-here-is-one-more-.aspx">
Ivory carving in France</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bwsmigel.info/GEOL.115.ESSAYS/Gemology.Ivory.html">
Gemological properties of ivory</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.antiquespider.com/information/elephant_preservation.asp">
On The Preservation of Elephants by www.antiquespider.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ivoryandart.com/servlet/the-template/mammothivoryfake/Page/">
Learn About Different Ivories and Identifying Fakes</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/07/14/kenya-ivory-rhino-horn-se_n_231641.html">
Kenya Ivory, Rhino Horn Seizure Tops 660 Pounds</weblink> by Tom Odula, <it>The Huffington Post</it>, July 14, 2009</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ivorycarvings.org">
Ivory Carvings</weblink> All about ivory Carvings</entry>
</list>


</p>
<p>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
