<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 93 $ on 27.02.2011 20:10:00[cl1n033] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Crown prince</title>
<id>236210</id>
<revision>
<id>375735765</id>
<timestamp>2010-07-27T14:17:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Gergis</username>
<id>368323</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>:Heirs to the throne</category>
<category>:Noble titles</category>
<category>:Princes</category>
<category>:Royal titles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>


File:Crowd awaiting Crown Prince Tokyo Dec1916.jpg|thumb|right|190px|Throngs before the Imperial Palace in Japan awaiting the appearance of the Crown Prince Hirohito for the recent proclamation of his official recognition as the heir apparent to the Japanese Imperial Throne -- <it>New York Times,</it> 1916.]] <p>

A <b>crown prince</b> or <b>crown princess</b> is the heir or heiress apparent to the throne in a royal or imperial monarchy. The wife of a crown prince is also titled <it>crown princess</it>. </p>
<p>

The term is now borne as a title only in Thailand and the Scandinavian monarchies; but it may also be used generically to refer to the person or position of the heir apparent in other kingdoms. However, heirs apparent to non-imperial and non-royal monarchies (i.e., wherein the hereditary sovereign holds a title below that of king/queen, e.g., grand duke or prince), crown prince is not used as a title, although it is sometimes used as a synonym for <it>heir apparent</it>.</p>
<p>

In Europe, where primogeniture governs succession to all monarchies except those of the Papacy and Andorra, the eldest <it>son</it> (Denmark, Spain, United Kingdom) or eldest <it>child</it> (Belgium, Netherlands, Norway, and Sweden) of the current monarch fills the role of crown prince or princess, depending upon whether females of the dynasty enjoy personal succession rights. The eldest <it>living</it> child of a monarch is sometimes not the heir apparent or crown prince, because that position can be held by a descendant of a <it>deceased</it> older child who, by "right of representation", inherits the same place in the line of succession that would be held by the ancestor if he or she were still living (e.g., Carl Gustaf, Duke of Jämtland was <it>de facto</it> Crown Prince of Sweden from 1950 to 1973, as the senior grandson by male primogeniture of King Gustaf VI Adolf of Sweden, although the former Prince Sigvard, Duke of Uppland was Gustaf VI's eldest living son, and Prince Bertil, Duke of Halland his eldest living dynastic son during those years).</p>
<p>

In some monarchies, those of the Middle East for example, in which primogeniture is not the decisive factor in dynastic succession, a person may not possess the title or status of crown prince by right of birth, but may obtain (and lose) it as a result of an official designation made on some other legal or traditional basis, e.g., former Crown Prince Hassan bin Talal of Jordan. </p>
<p>

Compare heir apparent and heir presumptive. In Scandinavian kingdoms, the heir presumptive to the crown holds a different title than the heir apparent; <it>Hereditary Prince</it> (German: <it>Erbprinz</it>, French: <it>prince héréditaire</it>). That is also the title borne by the heirs apparent of Luxembourg and Liechtenstein, and by the heir or heiress presumptive of Monaco. In the Germanic monarchies abolished in 1918, hereditary prince, rather than crown prince, was also the title borne by the heirs apparent of the kingdoms of Bavaria, Hanover, Saxony, and Württemberg, as well as those of grand duchies, of sovereign duchies and principalities, and of mediatized princely families.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Christian/western traditional titles</st>
<p>

Many monarchies use or did use unique titles for their heirs apparent, often of historical origin:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dauphin (Kingdom of France); originally not unique but an alternative comital title in chief of the Dauphiné region</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince Royal (Kingdom of France, monarchy of 1789-91; and July Monarchy)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Diadoch</it> (Kingdom of Greece); translated as <it>Crown Prince</it> but literally <it>successor</it> (see also below)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Prince Imperial</it> (Empire of Brazil, Second French Empire, and Empire of Mexico)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Rex iunior</it> (Kingdom of Hungary); i.e., "Junior King", so called because he was crowned during the life of the incumbent (often his father)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Tsesarevich</it> (Imperial Russia); commonly but mistakenly confused with Tsarevich</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince Royal of Portugal (<it>Príncipe Real de Portugal e dos Algarves</it>) (Kingdom of Portugal); for the heir presumptive since 1815)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Braganza (Kingdom of Portugal); when the House of Braganza inherited the throne (1640), this title passed to the royal heir and was used together with Prince of Brazil (until 1815), and Prince Royal of Portugal (after 1815)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Duke of Barcelos (Kingdom of Portugal); used in conjunction with <it>Duke of Braganza</it> by royal heirs of the House of Braganza</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Cornwall (former Kingdom of England); now used in conjunction with <it>Prince of Wales''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Rothesay (former Scotland); now used in lieu of <it>Prince of Wales''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Asturias, Kingdom of Spain; from the former Kingdom of Castile, retained as principal title after unification with Aragon and, later, Navarre</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Prince of Gerona (former Crown of Aragon); this title was always used in conjunction with other three titles for the heir of the Crown of Aragon crown: Duke of Montblanc, Count of Cervera, Lord of Balaguer; now the four titles are used in conjunction with <it>Prince of Asturias</it>.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Prince of Viana (former Kingdom of Navarre); now used in conjunction with <it>Prince of Asturias''</it></entry>
</list>

Some monarchies have used (although not always <it>de jure</it>) a territorial title for heirs apparent which, though often perceived as a crown princely title, is not automatically hereditary. It generally requires a specific conferral by the sovereign, which may be withheld.  </p>
<p>

Current and past titles in this category include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Brabant (Kingdom of Belgium); does not automatically descend by primogeniture, e.g.,  never held by Albert, Prince of Liège after his childless brother became king </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Estonia and Laland (Denmark; during, at least, reigns of Christopher II and Valdemar IV)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

HH the Crown Prince (Kuwait)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Norway (Denmark-Norway); in 15th-19th centuries</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Orange (Netherlands)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Wales (England, Great Britain, United Kingdom)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

King of the Romans (Holy Roman Empire) – an elective, rather than an inherited title, for the designated successor – usually the son, but sometimes the brother – of the Emperor</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Grão-Para (title of the eldest son of the Brazilian heir)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

King of Rome (First French Empire)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Sparta, Kingdom of Greece; used briefly, <it>within</it> Greece, only by Prince Constantine, during reign of his father King George I</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Piedmont (title of the eldest son of the King of Sardinia, and then of the King of Italy, when it was alternated with Prince of Naples)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Brazil (title of the Portuguese heir from 1645 to 1815)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Beira (title of the eldest son of the Portuguese heir)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Scania (Sweden during the time when Magnus IV of Sweden also was King of Terra Scania)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Ani (Kingdom of West Armenia)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Turnovo (Kingdom of Bulgaria)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Alba Julia (Kingdom of Romania)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Grand Duke of Grahavo (Kingdom of Montenegro)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of Venice (see Prince Eugène de Beauharnais); for the heir presumptive to Napoleon I in his Kingdom of Italy</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Duke of Calabria (Kingdom of the Two Sicilies)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other specific traditions</st>
<p>

Islamic cultures:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In Egypt, <it>Prince of the Sa'id</it>, meaning <it>Prince of Upper Egypt''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In Persia, Qajar dynasty, the full style was <it>Vala Hazrat-i-Humayun Vali Ahad, Shahzada</it> (given name) <it>Mirza</it>, i.e His August Imperial Highness the Heir Apparent, Prince ...; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the above component <b>vali ahad</b> meaning 'successor by virtue of a covenant' (or various forms and etymological derivations) was adopted by many oriental monarchies, even some non-Muslim, e.g. <b>Walet</b> as alternative title for the Nepali (Hindu) royal heir apparent; first used Crown Prince Trailokya in the middle of the nineteenth century, taken from the Mughal title 'Vali Ahad' </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Hindu tradition (Indian subcontinent):
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Yuvaraja was part of the full title in many princely states of India, e.g.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

in Kashmir, the heir apparent was styled <it>Maharaj Kumar Shri Yuvaraj</it> (personal name) <it>Singhji Bahadur''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tika </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nepal, where the King was styled Maharajadhiraja:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

the heir apparent was styled: <it>Sri Sri Sri Sri Sri</it> <b>Yuvarajadhiraj</b> ('Young King of Kings', i.e. Crown Prince) (personal name) <it>Bir Bikram Shah Deva</it>;</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

the eldest son of the heir apparent was styled: <it>Sri Sri Sri Sri Sri </it>'Nava Yuvaraj<b><it> ('Young Crown Prince') (personal name) </it></b><b>Bir Bikram Shah Deva''</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Far Eastern traditions:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The cognates of Chinese Chinese <it>Huang Taizi</it> (皇太子, "Great Imperial Son"): Japanese <it>Kōtaishi</it>, Korean <it>Hwangtaeja</it> (황태자), Vietnamese <it>Hoàng Thái Tử</it> -- if a son of the reigning emperor.  In case the heir is a grandson, the title <it>Huang Taisun</it> (皇太孫), <it>Kōtaison</it>, <it>Hwangtaeson</it> (황태손), and <it>Hoàng Thái Tôn</it>, literally "Great Imperial Grandson", are used</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

During the Joseon Dynasty in Korea, the crown prince was referred as Dong-gung(동궁, 東宮) due to the location of his residence from the main palace.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Southeast Asian traditions: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Siam Makutrajakuman (สยามมกุฎราชกุมาร) in Thailand since 1886.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Krom Phrarajawangboworn Sathanmongkol or Phra Maha Uparaja or commonly called Wang Na (or Front Palace) in Thailand prior to 1886.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kanjeng Gusti Pangeran Adipati Anom in Yogyakarta sultanate and Surakarta, Indonesia.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Raja Muda or Tengku Mahkota in the Malay sultanates of Malaysia.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pengiran Muda Mahkota  in Brunei</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Equivalents in other cultures:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jaguar Prince (Mesoamerica)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ka Haku O Hawaii or</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Caesar (title) (since the tetrarchy) and Consors imperii</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Princeps iuventutis</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prince of the blood</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Crown Prince Party" of the People's Republic of China</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

List of heirs apparent</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources and references</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://4dw.net/royalark/">
RoyalArk- see each present country</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.heraldica.org/topics/france/napoleon.htm#titles_italy">
Heraldica.org- here napoleonic section</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
